V-12 Program (United States Department of the Navy) Records UA213
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
V-12 Program (United States Department of the Navy) Records
1941 -- 1980
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Navy V-12 Program at Tufts College
UA213
4.13 Linear Feet 9 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: V-12 student index cards and Unprocessed accessions.
Custodial History
This UA collection was created in February 2011 to house V-12 records (so-called School of War card indices) found in the locked basement vault of Ballou Hall in the summer of 2010 and an unprocessed box of records previously cataloged under MS029 (V-12 memorabilia). The V-12/School of War grade sheets remain in UA072. Susanne Belovari, Archivist for Reference and Collections
Scope and Contents
This collection contains student index cards from the V-12 program, photographs, and subject files. Tufts University's Air Force Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC) program is one significant topic in this collection.
Biographical / Historical
The Navy V-12 Program was established in 1942 as part of the Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps to provide accelerated officer training at American colleges and universities in support of the war effort. During its existence at Tufts, more than 4,000 officers received their training on the Medford campus. Students enrolled in the program were able to complete their college studies, supplemented with special military training prior to being commissioned in the navy. The School for War Service was organized to administer the naval programs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Student activities
- V-12 Student index cards, 1943 -- 1946; UA213.001; 1.6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains student index cards from the V-12 program.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from the date of creation. Open for research.
  - School of War Program cards [V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy], 1943-11; UA213.001.001 (Box 1)
    75 years from the date of creation.
    Program cards (alphabetical run A - part of T) include name of student, term beginning (Nov. 1943), terms already completed, major department or curriculum courses taken, credits and grades, and program acronyms.
  - School of War Program cards [V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy], 1943-11 -- 1944-07; UA213.001.002 (Box 2)
    Continues alphabetical run from box 1. Program cards include name of student, term beginning (Nov. 1943 as well as July 1944), terms already completed, major department or curriculum courses taken, credits and grades, and program acronyms.
    See box 5 for envelope filled with student program cards from 1944 that were not interfiled (reason unknown).
  - School of War Program cards [V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy], November 1944, 1944-11; UA213.001.003 (Box 3)
    The complete alphabetical run of program cards include name of student, term beginning (Nov. 1944), terms already completed, major department or curriculum courses taken, credits and grades, and program acronyms. See box 5 for envelope filled with student program cards from 1944 that were not interfiled (reason unknown).
  - School of War Program cards [V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy], 1945-03 -- 1945-07; UA213.001.004 (Box 4)
    Program cards include name of student, term beginning (complete alphabetical run for term starting March 1945, alphabetical run A-P for July 1945 term), terms already completed, major department or curriculum courses taken, credits and grades, and program acronyms.
  - School of War Program cards [V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy], 1945-07 -- 1945-11; UA213.001.005 (Box 5)
    Program cards include name of student, term beginning (rest of alphabetical run P-Z for term July 1945, complete alphabetical run for term November 1945), terms already completed, major department or curriculum courses taken, credits and grades, and program acronyms.
    Also included at the end of the program cards are an envelope of cards that had not been interfiled from 1944 as well as a card with 'missing grades and 'removed' students.
  - School of War Program cards [V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy], 1946-03; UA213.001.006 (Box 6)
    Program cards include name of student, term beginning (complete alphabetical run for term March 1946), terms already completed, major department or curriculum courses taken, credits and grades, and program acronyms.
    Also included are empty program cards and a letter 'Office of the Registrar - School of War Service' dated February 1, 1946 informing advisers of non-Engineering Navy Students about procedures and NROTC as well as V-5 requirements. The letter is filed with the cards because it was used as paper to list student names on the back for the index with capitalized note in pencil 'major choices for Nils Y. Wessell).
  - Index of Navy Students A-L, 1943 -- 1946; UA213.001.007 (Box 7)
    Open for research.
  - Index of Navy Students M-Z, 1943 -- 1946; UA213.001.008 (Box 8)
- Additional accessions, UA213.000010
  - Box of documents and photos, ROTC, Air force, and office of vocational rehabilitation, 1941 -- 1980; UA213-001 (Box data_value_missing_30f7f2369278b1267b2bea6684d1fadf, Box 1)
    Box found spring 2001, not previously cataloged. Majority of materials focus on Army ROTC. Box includes photographs of ROTC groups, records which address the close of the Army ROTC program, and complete roster and class schedules of Navy students enrolled at Tufts College 1943. Material is believed to have been accessioned from the Office of Vocational Rehabilitation. From green barcode list: "Miller subject files mixup, labeled photographs navy and ROTC"